<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Cicd on Robin's blog</title><link>https://kaveland.no/tags/cicd/</link><description>Recent content in Cicd on Robin's blog</description><generator>Hugo -- 0.145.0</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 21 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://kaveland.no/tags/cicd/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Deploying to BunnyCDN and protecting Norway from drop bears</title><link>https://kaveland.no/posts/2025-04-20-deploying-to-bunnycdn/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kaveland.no/posts/2025-04-20-deploying-to-bunnycdn/</guid><description>&lt;p>Not long ago, I wrote about &lt;a href="https://kaveland.no/posts/2025-04-14-running-containers-on-the-cheap">running containers&lt;/a> as part of moving my hobby projects to European cloud providers. That post was focused on running good old Linux servers. I briefly mentioned &lt;a href="https://bunny.net">BunnyCDN&lt;/a> but didn’t dive into the details. It&amp;rsquo;s time to dive into the details!&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="what-the-flark-is-a-cdn">What the flark is a CDN?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>A &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Content_delivery_network">content delivery network&lt;/a> is a geographically distributed network of servers that can deliver content to your users, close to where they are. It&amp;rsquo;s useful, because the speed of light isn&amp;rsquo;t fast enough to make pages load quickly across the other side of the globe. Seriously, the fastest thing in the universe cannot deliver cat pictures to people quickly enough. By using a CDN, you can geographically distribute assets like cat pictures, HTML, CSS, JavaScript, video files, fonts and much more.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Using short lived postgres servers for testing</title><link>https://kaveland.no/posts/2024-05-27-shortlived-postgres-servers/</link><pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kaveland.no/posts/2024-05-27-shortlived-postgres-servers/</guid><description>&lt;p>Database servers are usually long-lived, and important parts of the infrastructure
that we build on. We rarely set them up from scratch, because we have to take
such good care of them over time. I think this causes a lot of people to think
that setting up a database server is some mysteriously difficult ordeal. To be clear,
that&amp;rsquo;s actually true, if you need high availability and a solid recovery point objective.
But there are a lot of use cases where that&amp;rsquo;s overkill, for example short-lived
test environments, or CI/CD pipelines.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>