<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Writing on Robin's blog</title><link>https://kaveland.no/tags/writing/</link><description>Recent content in Writing on Robin's blog</description><generator>Hugo -- 0.145.0</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 20:30:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://kaveland.no/tags/writing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The librarian immediately attempts to sell you a vuvuzela</title><link>https://kaveland.no/posts/2025-06-06-library/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 20:30:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kaveland.no/posts/2025-06-06-library/</guid><description>&lt;p>Imagine entering the biggest library in the world. You peer down an incredibly long aisle with wooden bookshelves brimming with books. You can see multiple such corridors, all lit with a comfortable warm light. There&amp;rsquo;s a rich smell of old paper. You can hear some muted voices, perhaps arguing in a whisper. It&amp;rsquo;s perfect, but vast and difficult to make sense of. Just this day, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t feel like such a terrible ordeal to just wander for a while, see where your legs take you. Maybe you&amp;rsquo;ll find something interesting completely by accident? The prospect is both exhilarating and daunting. The library appears endless, it feels like you could potentially find all sorts of exotic and interesting book collections.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>To create, or be consumed? That is the question</title><link>https://kaveland.no/posts/2025-05-06-produce-or-consume/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kaveland.no/posts/2025-05-06-produce-or-consume/</guid><description>&lt;p>This is a note to myself about how to prioritize wisely. Or perhaps, it is an effort to commit to text a healthy mindset for myself. I have been trying to get into this mindset over a timeframe of some years now. I am making some progress, but it&amp;rsquo;s slow and not without setbacks. You can read it if you&amp;rsquo;d like, but this is my own advice for &lt;em>me&lt;/em>. It may not apply to you.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Building documentation for Eugene</title><link>https://kaveland.no/posts/2024-05-20-building-docsite-for-eugene/</link><pubDate>Mon, 20 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kaveland.no/posts/2024-05-20-building-docsite-for-eugene/</guid><description>&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;ve been busy working on a &lt;a href="https://kaveland.no/eugene">documentation site for eugene&lt;/a>, and I
think it&amp;rsquo;s starting to look pretty good. I wanted to write down some of
my thoughts around the process so far, and some of the things I&amp;rsquo;ve learned.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s just been a few days since I ported my blog to hugo, so since I was
already feeling like I was up to speed on that, I decided I&amp;rsquo;d try using it
for the eugene documentation too. I experimented with a few different
setups around the &lt;a href="https://themes.gohugo.io/themes/hugo-book/">hugo-book&lt;/a>
theme, but it ended up feeling like I was having to configure a bit
too much for my taste. I think it looked really nice, but the setup
felt a bit janky and complicated, with having the submodules and
everything in the eugene repo itself. I think my problem here is
just that doing this with hugo would require me to learn more about
hugo than I&amp;rsquo;m ready for right now.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Moving the blog to Hugo</title><link>https://kaveland.no/posts/2024-05-18-moving-to-hugo/</link><pubDate>Sat, 18 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kaveland.no/posts/2024-05-18-moving-to-hugo/</guid><description>&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;ve been using &lt;a href="https://github.com/getpelican/pelican">pelican&lt;/a> for my blog for
a while now, and I don&amp;rsquo;t really have anything negative to say about it. But for
a while, I&amp;rsquo;ve been wanting a more minimal theme. I ended up on the front page
of hacker news a couple of times, and the old theme had my face on all the
pages, which made me feel a bit uncomfortable. I was looking at some other
themes around the web, and I found &lt;a href="https://github.com/adityatelange/hugo-PaperMod">PaperMod&lt;/a>
which I absolutely loved. I followed instructions for how to set it up, and
it turns out that it only took me an hour or two to get everything up and
running. I guess I have to give credit to where credit is due, both Hugo and
PaperMod are really well-made, and easy to use. There&amp;rsquo;s a lot more stuff that
Hugo can do, but I think I have everything I need set up for now.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>