<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Seaborn on Robin's blog</title><link>https://kaveland.no/tags/seaborn/</link><description>Recent content in Seaborn on Robin's blog</description><generator>Hugo -- 0.145.0</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 19:30:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://kaveland.no/tags/seaborn/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Using SQL to turn all the buses around</title><link>https://kaveland.no/posts/2025-05-28-turning-the-bus-sql/</link><pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 19:30:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://kaveland.no/posts/2025-05-28-turning-the-bus-sql/</guid><description>&lt;p>I have a small hobby project over at &lt;a href="https://kollektivkart.arktekk.no/">kollektivkart.arktekk.no&lt;/a> that is for visualizing changes in public transit in Norway. For some time I&amp;rsquo;ve been wanting to do some visualizations on public transit lines. For example, plot the mean delay at each stop used by a line over time.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When trying to do some concept work on this, I discovered a puzzle in the data! Many lines go in two opposite directions. Here in Trondheim, Line 3 goes from Loholt to Hallset, but also from Hallset to Loholt. The way I can tell these apart is to look up the &lt;em>direction&lt;/em> in the data. Within a line, there can be variations in each direction. Some services might skip some stops, or depending on how you look at it, others visit extra stops. But these are variations on a theme, and it probably makes sense to group them together to preserve our sanity and not get 12 different plots for each line—2 should be plenty!&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Norwegian Wild Salmon Fishing Ban of 2024</title><link>https://kaveland.no/posts/2024-06-27-salmon-ban/</link><pubDate>Thu, 27 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kaveland.no/posts/2024-06-27-salmon-ban/</guid><description>&lt;p>For this blog post, I&amp;rsquo;m trying something different. This is a jupyter notebook that I&amp;rsquo;m using to study some data, and just dumping my brain out in text. If I can easily export this to a format that works with &lt;a href="https://gohugo.io/">hugo&lt;/a>, this might become a common occurrence.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For this one, I&amp;rsquo;m leaving the code in. There isn&amp;rsquo;t that much of it, but I think it&amp;rsquo;s fun to show how much visualization per
line of code you can get with &lt;a href="https://seaborn.pydata.org/">seaborn&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://pandas.pydata.org/">pandas&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>