<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Thoughts on Robin's blog</title><link>https://kaveland.no/tags/thoughts/</link><description>Recent content in Thoughts on Robin's blog</description><generator>Hugo -- 0.145.0</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 20:30:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://kaveland.no/tags/thoughts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The librarian immediately attempts to sell you a vuvuzela</title><link>https://kaveland.no/posts/2025-06-06-library/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 20:30:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kaveland.no/posts/2025-06-06-library/</guid><description>&lt;p>Imagine entering the biggest library in the world. You peer down an incredibly long aisle with wooden bookshelves brimming with books. You can see multiple such corridors, all lit with a comfortable warm light. There&amp;rsquo;s a rich smell of old paper. You can hear some muted voices, perhaps arguing in a whisper. It&amp;rsquo;s perfect, but vast and difficult to make sense of. Just this day, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t feel like such a terrible ordeal to just wander for a while, see where your legs take you. Maybe you&amp;rsquo;ll find something interesting completely by accident? The prospect is both exhilarating and daunting. The library appears endless, it feels like you could potentially find all sorts of exotic and interesting book collections.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>To create, or be consumed? That is the question</title><link>https://kaveland.no/posts/2025-05-06-produce-or-consume/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kaveland.no/posts/2025-05-06-produce-or-consume/</guid><description>&lt;p>This is a note to myself about how to prioritize wisely. Or perhaps, it is an effort to commit to text a healthy mindset for myself. I have been trying to get into this mindset over a timeframe of some years now. I am making some progress, but it&amp;rsquo;s slow and not without setbacks. You can read it if you&amp;rsquo;d like, but this is my own advice for &lt;em>me&lt;/em>. It may not apply to you.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>