<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Programming on Robin's blog</title><link>https://kaveland.no/tags/programming/</link><description>Recent content in Programming on Robin's blog</description><generator>Hugo -- 0.145.0</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 26 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://kaveland.no/tags/programming/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>It's okay to have no idea what you're doing and try anyway</title><link>https://kaveland.no/posts/2025-04-26-no-idea/</link><pubDate>Sat, 26 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kaveland.no/posts/2025-04-26-no-idea/</guid><description>&lt;p>When I was a kid, I thought adults knew everything there was to know. When I was a junior developer, I thought the senior developers knew everything there was to know about software.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As anyone who has made some progression in life knows, nobody gives you the big manual with all the answers when you level up. You&amp;rsquo;ll still be you. Just with more responsibility and more experience. But the experience does not come from age, it comes from actually having to try. It&amp;rsquo;s okay to have no idea what you&amp;rsquo;re doing and try anyway. It will make you better.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>What if that isn't a bool?</title><link>https://kaveland.no/posts/2025-01-08-what-if-it-isnt-a-bool/</link><pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kaveland.no/posts/2025-01-08-what-if-it-isnt-a-bool/</guid><description>&lt;p>A common way that code grows difficult to reason about is increasing the number
of things you must keep in your head simultaneously to understand it. Often,
this simply happens by adding one attribute, one variable, one column at a
time. Some people are gifted with a great capacity for working memory, but most
of us aren&amp;rsquo;t &amp;ndash; having to hold the state of 5 variables in your head
simultaneously to understand a piece of code may be pushing it far, according to
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Working_memory">this&lt;/a> article from wikipedia:&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>